- welcome to meditating with younger
Becky I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
carbon scientists at the University of
Toronto where I academically teach is
scientifically study phenomena such as
mindfulness Insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience
higher states of consciousness
cultivation of wisdom inspiration to
enlightenment I've also been practicing
the pasta meditation medical temptation
Tai Chi Chuan for over 29 years and
teaching them close to 20 years if
you're joining us for the first time
welcome but you should know that this is
a progressive course the introductory
course is done and we are now moving on
to more advanced material what you can
do is go to the notes in the description
of this video you'll find links both do
less than one immediately and then you
can joint keep meeting with us but do
less than one and then maybe every
Saturday or Sunday do another one of the
lessons and eventually you'll catch up
with us so today is a new day and that's
why I'm actually standing a couple of
reminders we have the new as I announce
next time we're going to be doing a new
thing so Mondays are going to alternate
between a dharma day in which I teach a
new principle in practice and in PI a
day in which I will take you through the
entire sequence so you get a sense of
the whole ecology that we're doing all
at once so last Monday was a dominate
and that's what I'm going to review it
right now a few more things before we
begin the review please like this stream
to increases visibility in the YouTube
algorithm every day we meet at the end
of it there is a QA please keep the Q as
limited to questions about this course
and the purposes of their end for more
encompassing questions please come to
the live stream Q&A that I do on YouTube
every third Friday of the month and that
for this month I'll be June 19 at 3 p.m.
Eastern
all right I think that's it we need to
do for now
so let's review what we're doing here
we're going to go over some of the I
won't explain add up some of the
principles but we're just going to begin
the review of what we did last time so
the first is embracing the tree and so
remember we want to always first before
we even begin we wanted to Luigi which
is that basic standing posture I'm going
to turn the sign on again to help you
okay so my feet are about shoulder width
apart and I make sure my totally toes
are pointing forward if my toes are out
like this it means I'm actually locking
my knees of my hips right and I want to
that would massively reduces my
sensitivity and my flexibility so what I
want to do is I want to shoot make sure
my toes both shoulder width apart
my feet shoulder width apart they should
say my toes going forward I put my hands
out and notice how you might be tempted
to do this all right see how my elbows
are rolled up let them roll down as if
there's weights pulling your elbows down
okay
I open my hands then I start to sit as
I'm going to sit on a stool I bend my
knees and I tuck my coccyx in and then I
make sure my shoulders are open and I
let my hands fall back and I have my
aides under my armpits here okay and I
put a little tiny bend in my head a
little tiny bent it straighten out my
spine okay so that's one G and it's
important to practice standing that way
I won't stand there for very long
because you have limited time but
standing this this is part of Jen jump
John John is the part of economy which
we are standing and what we're doing is
we're cultivating very comprehensively
and dynamically integrated mind body
awareness
okay now or in would you know what we're
going to do is we're going to begin with
embracing the tree I bring my hands up
but like a hand width apart notice that
my elbows again are not up they're
rolled down my elbows are below my
wrists my wrists are below my shoulders
right and it's like I'm squeezing a big
ball spongy ball this way and also this
way
and I'm squeezing a Bungie ball a big
Bungie ball between my knees and I'm
sitting on it so I'm squishing it
downward and inward squishing it inward
and inward displaying inward this way
and then we do the baby breathing that
we do in the pasta and it letter
and we publicly do this longer pick a
multiple of four for how many breasts
you can do for a 12:20 and then do it
for that many then we we move to this
process proposition say we inhale so
this is the remember what yang is going
out inhale and then as we exhale we feel
that spongy ball between our hands let's
do that three more times
remember throughout that your weight is
not on your heels or your toes but in
between center of your foot maybe feel
your route for meditation reaching down
and back to the center and now we're
going to do fire on their belly we bring
the hands in and we feel that warmth
between our hands and we clench the
sphincter muscle for our come here on
our palate you feel that heat in the
Dante end
now the microcosmic are even closed come
here as I inhale tracing all the way up
to the top of my head and then as I
exhale it's like you're also called the
old man stroking this beard it comes in
front smoking a long beard down okay
I feel your Center and root from your
meditation practice I'm going to add in
one new thing last time we went directly
into the two R's
breathing now we're going to add in
something to get your hands up and
there's another price so this is a
little bit more than review I'm actually
layering something new want to know
review this again on Friday understand
sideways you can see what I'm doing my
hands are here
we've just finished stroking the beard
and what's going to happen is I'm gonna
do this practice and what it is is my
tea on my hands
are rotating they're rotating clockwise
by my right hand goes out and then my
left hand goes out a little bit farther
with a my right hand a little bit
farther and you're circling and what
you're doing here is you're actually
enacting the symbolically reciprocal
opening a reciprocal opening first of
like the energy center with the work so
you do that and you come up and you do
the heart reciprocal opening of the
heart
and the mind and now the spirit which
represents the function of
self-transcendence up and this is how
you get your hands up for doing the the
two R's prevail so let's review we do
this here here here
so energy heart mind and spirit and then
we're here and we do what I showed you
laughs on Monday oh oh as video and then
all if you're getting into a bathtub and
is now here in front of your third-eye
[Applause]
heart
[Music]
oh yeah and in turn 3/4 normally
wouldn't move we tried it something that
will help with the most difficult of the
practices I've shown you so far which is
really missile so might wait let's start
my weight is now centered I'm going to
shift slightly to the right and what I'm
going to do is this is going to scoop
across and this is going to rise up like
this and I inhale and then this cuts
down this cuts up and then this is going
to turn to a scoop and this is going to
turn into an elbow and elbow stroke like
this so as I exhale right there now
inhaling this come this goes down into a
scoop this comes off into an elbow then
keep the right just keep cycling so
maybe only to like exhaling to the right
inhaling to the left
exhaling to the right and notice on
slowly I'm turning my hips to turn my
heart and my head right I'm not moving
from my head and dragging my hips my
hips are turning and that turns my heart
which turns my head lift shifting the
weight and try to get a continuous
in-breath and left continuous out-breath
to the right now feeling a lean like
this is to get that prone feeling that
you're wheeling silk enough effort that
you would reel the silk but not so much
that you would snap it my knees don't do
this I try to keep that spongy ball
between my knees
okay and we come back the closing
exercise always do this bringing down
the heavens begin breath scooping up
wave of relaxation on the front of your
face front of your chest from the drive
bill in front of your legs
sinking three feet into the earth begin
breath scooping up wave of relaxation
back your head back your body back your
legs sinking three feet into the earth
in big scooping up for the head throat
chest abdomen legs three feet into the
earth
big scooping up all three at once
back into wuji position okay please take
a seat
a soon you'll need to adjust the cameras
like they imagine great thank you son
all right so let's get into correct
posture please set your phones - do not
disturb and we're going to sit for 12
minutes - it will sit for 12 minutes so
we can also get a little bit of time
pressures will begin when I say begin
begin
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you call T we did in your
practice with you over gating
consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay we'll see if we have a few
questions waiting for them to come up on
the screen right now
so we have one from Karima can you
recommend an example of mind body fast
besides flow State
glad you're addressing the EO on Monday
yes I think another example of a mind
body fasting from egocentric self our
personal processing is when you get into
the project state in fact that's one of
the deep benefits of Polishness state I
want to choose my language very
carefully here alright but it's just
that state of non-duality removes you
from ego centrism and it also
simultaneously enhances your sense of
connectedness to mind and body and to
the world I know that sort of sounds
like like an oxymoron it because the ego
says the only way you grasp the world is
to grasp it right control and the only
way he grasps mind and body is through
control and dominance in fact maybe even
that language is telling the only way to
connect to the world is to grasp it and
the only way to connect to mind audience
to grasp it but in non-duality you're
deeply connected
well not grasp it and it's it and that's
why it's also a deep realization of the
being mode so that would be another
clear example Victoria hi Victoria
Victoria former student of mindfulness
good to be my guest teaching you again
just knowing that you're there is it's
wonderful so John please show us the
foot stance for Reed reeling the silk
short so I'll do it now face on I think
you can see my feet just think of
they're actually Jason is pub that way
comes down like feet so my feet
it's basically the wuji stance and when
I'm reeling the silk I'm not this is a
mistake I'm not turning my feet
I'm staying rooted and also trying as
much as it could not turn my needs I'm
trying to move my knees more in and out
to turn my hips rather than folding them
in and my feet are staying in exactly
the same way they were in Wu Jie
Algernon
Deimos should we keep our feet firmly
planted not on ball not on heel while
going side to side in the frizzle
pressure which we allow our feet to
slightly lift no keep your feet firmly
planted that's another great question
your feet are firmly planted you're in
the center of your foot and you are like
a tree the roots of your tree are
reaching deep into the stillness of the
earth and the wind of spirit is blowing
through your branches to use some of the
poetic imagery okay so that's what
you're after pleasure without is kind of
question happy Bret that's good to have
you here as always with the initial body
scan how long should it take
approximately how long to focus on each
body part I usually you know just as
long as to mindfully recite you know you
know the looking the loosening the
listening letting it flow and letting it
go and then it's next Dharma day I will
teach you another sitted Qigong practice
each one practice and then a
corresponding purely mental practice of
yin and yang and which is another way in
which you can find your root I don't
think it should be taught as the first
way of finding the root I think the way
I taught you is the foundational way but
you'll then how you'll be able to layer
that on and that usually gives it's like
scale up equation there's two slightly
different practices for directed towards
the same goal converging on it but often
give you a more sensitive awareness of
it
but usually just enough time to recite
each one of those for maybe a breath or
two and then go forward a DMZ MF I'm not
going to try to pronounce do anymore
in our daily practice ship moving
practice be done before or after certain
practice before she'd be done before the
part the point about the moon practice
is to engage the cerebellum cortex loop
it is also to energize you it's to get
in the state we're both right the the
tracking network of the default mode
network are being activated in some ways
both the sympathetic and parasympathetic
system and it's energizing you while
getting you alert and sensitive and
routed and so it really facilitates
going deeper into the sitted practice so
when we do a PI a day that's what we'll
do with I will start and we will work
our way through the cheek on we will go
into the past non meta or
Akash nut and then we will do let Co
Divina quintessential if you recommend
keeping the tongue to the roof of your
mouth as when saying deep throughout the
process of aw and our face no you can
let your tongue open so in the on and on
you're trying to be as much like you
would be we use this is the imaginal use
of imagination under the magic narrator
head this is an imagine all right we're
pantomiming but it's a gestural
imagination we're interacting the world
we're using imagination to Train
perception and so try to make it as much
like what it would be like if you were
naturally experiencing on and then so
that's a good question I'm finding I
don't know if I'd gone all through that
previous question but I guess that's
enough for now Matthew McCready I'm
finding that my monkey - distractions
are changing over time from a singular
voice of Jamie tomorrow and a lot - two
or three voices at once yes I did sort
of forewarn that you will often discover
that there are multiple voices in your
head will I eventually pretend the
monkey mind or the distractions become
more
elaborate overtime eventually they will
fade away this is sort of enix that
right this sort of a general principle
the worst was it and that you've seen us
at even in sort of the scientific study
of classical oblivion conditioning and
operant conditioning right before your
pattern begins to extinguish you'll
often get sort of this spike in its
activity now I'm not talking like
suddenly for a day this would probably
happen for weeks or perhaps even months
but you'll get this and then and it's
challenging
precisely because that's when the most
work is being done but had it said to me
in person by people who taught me and
I've read it in multiple places when
things are feeling really good
not that that's bad or anything to be
but the things are when things are
feeling really good in your practice not
much change is occurring all right and
what's happening is you're building up
the skills the sensitivities the new
sense of self age and right agent arena
relationship all of that is being built
up and that's important but it when it's
a so you have to give it like when
things are sort of feeling really good
what you're doing is building up this
you know living dynamical system you
know the self rolling wheel of the way
and then when you get like lots of
distraction or resistance that's when
this is then being applied to the
process of transformation so typically
that expansion of the you know the
multiple voices as long as you're not
falling asleep okay as long as it's
clear that you're completely alert full
mindfulness then that indicates that
there's a change beginning in the
relationship to the monkey money it's it
used to be all like this in a single
voice and now it's opening up and you're
suddenly see how complex and varied it
is but that is ultimately a good thing
the deed Allah Allah he I hope I did not
mispronounce that forgive me if I did
one thing that I don't talk a lot about
because
largely ignorant I have read and I have
spoken to Muslim communities I have two
had two wonderful discussions the most
recent with Hudson surah on the
interrelationship between my work and
these practices and Islam and I handle
both of those conversations as special
it was very mutually beneficial but I
hesitate to speak any way of Islam
e-even the Sufi tradition within it is
fine because although it's closer
participated in practices and studied a
little bit more my connect my
understanding of Islam is very very
superficial and so I just wanted to
acknowledge that are not ignoring Islam
I am actually acting out of respect
proper respect for it so I read in some
books about Taoism chicon that it's
inadvisable to attempt these exercise
without transmission from a living
teacher may I consider that this work
with dr. BIR Vahey a living teacher yes
so I don't promote myself that way
because there's temptation there's
temptation to inflation there's
temptation to many things but your
question is an important question
answered in good faith and therefore in
response to that question I'm saying yes
thank you everyone for joining wonderful
questions wonderful questions really
wonderful I want to thank my dear friend
and techno major maher who's always
there
making miracles it's what most of us
live our days right but Maher spends his
days making miracles my beloved son
Jason who was literally behind the
scenes today making things happen moving
the camera very grateful to his help and
his participation he's doing the
practice with me
so I'm not sitting totally alone he's
here with me doing the practice sitting
with me that's much much appreciated
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified in the next video you'll find
links to the lecture series awakening
from the meeting crisis and to the
discussion series that the Ilocos series
of voices with ravi key where a lot of
these ideas and concepts and practices
are set into a much more comprehensive
and transformative framework way of life
a way of seeing a way of being and by
others who might benefit by sharing this
series this is the mote the best way I
can help people in this time and you're
helping me to help them that was here he
asked it a really good question there's
a bunch of people on the discord server
that do the practice they need to talk
afterwards there's the larger
communities in which many issues and
things are being discussed like some of
you from this practice I know are going
into the the discord server and that's
much appreciated there's a lot of great
discussion great reflection great
community us the vibrant dynamic life of
community is taking place there so
please check for a link in the
description of this video to the discord
server reminder we're doing this every
weekday morning at 9:30 Eastern Time
cognitive practice is more important
than share quantity of practice there is
no enemy worse than your own mind and
body
there is no friend no I like no to
companion upon the way better than your
own minded body be lamps unto yourselves
and to each other see you all tomorrow
take good care